Guide to the James Henry Rice Papers, 1885-1935 and undated, bulk 1910-1935
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
James Henry Rice papers 1885-1935 and undated (bulk 1910-1935)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Rice, James Henry, 1868-1935
18.1 linear feet Extent: 13,581 Items
Naturalist, conservationist, and local historian, of Wiggins (Colleton County), S.C. Chiefly personal correspondence (1910-1935) relating to the preservation of fauna in South Carolina and the Southeast, and to U.S. and South Carolina politics and history, family and business affairs, literature, and journalists. Includes a few clippings, photographs, and documents concerning Rice's life. Correspondents include William Watts Ball, Bernard Baruch, Coleman L. Blease, James F. Byrnes, Basil L. Gildersleeve, Ambrose E. Gonzales, William E. Gonzales, Dubose Heyward, Duncan C. Heyward, Thomas G. McLeod, Hugh McRae, Marie Conway Oemler, Gifford Pinchot, F. W. Ruckstull, Harry A. Slattery, and Benjamin R. Tillman.
RL.01098
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The James Henry Rice Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in 1956.
Collection Overview
The papers of James Henry Rice, Jr., naturalist, conservationist, and local historian, contain mainly correspondence reflecting his interest in natural history and the protection of wildlife; the history and contemporary politics of South Carolina; and family, business, artistic, and journalistic matters.
Material pertaining to Rice's activities as a naturalist and conservationist include letters, 1910-1913, to Rice from the Carolina Audubon Society and the National Association of Audubon Societies; correspondence, 1913-1917, with Robert Ridgway, E. H. Forbush, William Brewster, and officials of the National Museum in Washington, D.C., relating to Rice's work as inspector for the United States Biological Survey, concerning ornithology, particularly the breeding grounds, habitats, and migratory patterns of various Southeastern birds; long-term correspondence with Arthur Trezevant Wayne, author of Birds of South Carolina (Charleston: 1910); correspondence, 1927-1935, with William Chambers Coker, primarily concerning the identification of certain botanical specimens; correspondence concerning the Conservation Society of South Carolina; letters of naturalist Frank M. Chapman and explorer Carl E. Akely; correspondence with R. W. Shufeldt on natural history; letters concerning Secretary of the Interior Albert B. Fall and the Teapot Dome Scandal, 1921-1922; correspondence concerning forest lands in South Carolina with Courtlandt Braun, W. R. Mattoon of the United States Forest Service, and South Carolina state foresters, Lewis E. Staley, 1928-1931, and W. A. Smith, 1932; correspondence with W. T. Hornaday on conservation measures in the United States Congress, especially the Norbeck bill, 1929, which sought to impose hunting limits on ducks; correspondence, 1930, concerning the relationship of the National Association of Audubon Societies to the manufacturers of guns and ammunition; and letters relating to the meeting of the American Ornithologists Union in Charleston, South Carolina, 1928.
Correspondence on South Carolina politics and the state's history includes letters giving the views of various candidates for state and national office and commenting on elections and other political events; letters, 1905-1918, from United States Senator Benjamin R. Tillman; correspondence with Coleman L. Blease, governor of South Carolina, on the appointment of state game wardens, 1911-1913; correspondence relating to several articles written by Rice on local history and notable South Carolinians, especially "The Paladins of South Carolina," a series appearing in the State (Columbia, South Carolina) in 1922-1923, containing material on Martin W. Gary and Reconstruction in South Carolina, and Francis Wilkinson Pickens Butler's letters about Matthew Calbraith Butler; correspondence concerning the histories of the Rice, Elliott, Stuart, Clarkson, and Smith families, letters, 1929, discussing the life and career of J. Marion Sims; and correspondence, ca. 1926, with Dudley Jones on the history of the Presbyterian Church in South Carolina.
Items pertaining to business, literature, journalism and Rice's family include letters from George F. Mitchell on the development of coastal South Carolina; correspondence regarding a stock law for South Carolina, 1920-1921; correspondence with writers and academics including Marie Conway Oemler, Archibald Rutledge, Harriette Kershaw Leiding, William Peterfield Trent, Basil Lanneau Gildersleeve, and Ambrose E. Gonzales; correspondence with Dubose Heyward and John Bennett concerning the Poetry Society of South Carolina; letters from Francis Butler Simkins, Jr., 1922-1923, responding to Rice's criticism of his work; correspondence relating to Rice's work as agent for the Chee-Ha Combahee Company promoting the development of coastal lands, 1921-1922; letters concerning the development of Myrtle Beach, South Carolina,1925; a long personal correspondence with the sculptor Frederick Wellington Ruckstull containing news of Rice's family and exchanges of opinion on politics, art, and history; letters from many of Rice's friends in the 1930s showing the effects of the Depression; and letters discussing Franklin D. Roosevelt and the New Deal.
Printed matter and miscellaneous items in the collection include eulogies of Rice, several articles reflecting his interest in history and nature; report of the game warden of South Carolina, 1912; minutes of the 1932 meeting of the alumni association of the University of South Carolina; poems by Rice; and pamphlets and articles on natural history.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Ball, W. W. (William Watts), 1868-1952; Baruch, Bernard M. (Bernard Mannes), 1870-1965; Blease, Coleman Livingston, 1868-1942; Byrnes, James F. (James Francis), 1882-1972; Gildersleeve, Basil L. (Basil Lanneau), 1831-1924; Gonzales, Ambrose Elliott, 1857-1926; Gonzales, William E. (William Elliott), 1866-1937; Heyward, DuBose, 1885-1940; Heyward, Duncan Clinch, 1864-1943; McLeod, Thomas G. (Thomas Gordon), 1868-1932; McRae, Hugh, 1865-1943; Oemler, Marie Conway, 1879-1932; Pinchot, Gifford, 1865-1946; Rice family; Ruckstull, F. W. (Fred Wellington), 1853-1942; Slattery, Harry A.; Tillman, Benjamin R. (Benjamin Ryan), 1847-1918; Journalists; Wildlife conservation -- Southern States; South Carolina -- History; South Carolina -- Politics and government -- 1865-1950; United States -- Politics and government -- 1901-1953
Contents of Collection
- Correspondence Series, 1885-1935 and undated (bulk 1910-1935), (26 boxes)
  - 1885-1913 Feb. (Box 1)
  - 1913 Mar.-1919 May (Box 2)
  - 1919 June-1921 May (Box 3)
  - 1921 June-1922 Feb. (Box 4)
  - 1922 Mar.-Aug. 21 (Box 5)
  - 1922 Aug. 22-Nov. (Box 6)
  - 1922 Dec.-1923 Feb. (Box 7)
  - 1923 Mar.-July (Box 8)
  - 1923 Aug.-Dec. (Box 9)
  - 1924 Jan.-May (Box 10)
  - 1924 June-1925 Jan. (Box 11)
  - 1925 Feb.-Dec. (Box 12)
  - 1926-1927 Mar. (Box 13)
  - 1927 Apr.-1928 Mar. (Box 14)
  - 1928 Apr.-1929 Feb. (Box 15)
  - 1929 Mar.-Nov. (Box 16)
  - 1929 Dec-1930 Aug. (Box 17)
  - 1930 Sept.-1931 Apr. 14 (Box 18)
  - 1931 Apr. 15-Sept. (Box 19)
  - 1931 Oct.-1932 Dec. (Box 20)
  - 1933 Jan.-1934 Feb. (Box 21)
  - 1934 Mar.-July (Box 22)
  - 1934 Aug.-Dec. (Box 23)
  - 1935 Jan.-Dec. and undated (Box 24)
  - Undated (Box 25-26)
- Other Materials, (1 box)
  - Clippings (Box 26)
  - Financial papers
  - Miscellaneous items
  - Printed materials